Alexander E. Macdonald Papers,
Alexander E. Macdonald Papers and Photographs
- Professional Material, Series III
  - Legal Documents, Subseries A
    - In the matter of the investigation of the New York City Asylums, Subsubseries 3
      - Correspondence to Dent from "A Christian Endeavorer", 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence to A.E. Macdonald from illegible, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Transcript of testimony before State Commissioners in Lunacy, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Transcript of extracts of testimony of Commissioner Henry H. Porter, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - In the matter of the inquiry into the sanity of William C. Rhinelander, Subsubseries 4
      - Closing Argument of John M. Bowers, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Closing Argument of Hon. George M. Curtis, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Stokes Will Case, Subsubseries 5
      - Argument for Contestant by Theron G. Strong, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Selections from the Argument of Hon. William M. Evarts, on behalf of the Proponents and Brief upon the testimony relating to William E. Dodge Stokes, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Investigation into the Management and Affairs of the New York City Insane Asylum, on Ward's Island, by the Standing Committee on the Insane of the State Board of Charities, Subsubseries 6
      - Index, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Testimony June 29 (pp. 1-175), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - June 30 (pp. 176-284), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - July 1 (pp. 286-458), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - July 6 (pp. 459-687), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - July 7 (pp. 688-790), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - July 8 (pp. 791-1041), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - July 9 (pp. 1042-1225), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Macdonald v. Mayor, Alderman and Commonality of the City of New York, Subsubseries 7
      - Plantiff's Points, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Opinion of the General Term Supreme Court, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - In the matter of the application for the committment of Kate McEligot, an Alleged insane person, Subsubseries 8
      - Supreme Court order to show cause, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Exhibits A - G (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Patient History (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Deposition statement of Alexander E. Macdonald, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - In the matter of the investigation by the Board of Managers of the Manhattan State Hospital of the Steward's and other departments of said hospitals, Subsubseries 9
      - Testimony of Mr. Kimball, 1900; 5 copies (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Testimony of General Superintendent (April 16), 1900; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Testimony of Dr. Macdonald (April 18), 1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Testimony of Dr. Dent; miscellaneous related, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Testimony of Dr. Smith, [1900?]; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Testimony of Dr. John T. W. Rowe, 1900; 4 copies (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Testimony of Thomas O'Keefe, 1900; 4 copies (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Testimony of Michael F. Bradley, 1900; 4 copies (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Testimony of John L. Widdler, Jr., 1900; 3 copies (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Testimony of Mr. Murray [Assistant Steward?], [1900?] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Proceedings, Subsubseries 10
      - Incomplete transcript of testimony in unidentified case: pp. 161-217; 275-324; 275-324 (duplicate); 323-324 (duplicate); 891-906; 1463-1515; 1479-1515 (duplicate); 1737-1778, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Board of Estimate and Appointment, New York City. Community and Documents from the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction, Relating to the Future Provision for the Insane, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Reply of the Commissioners of Public Charities and Correction to the Charges Made by the Commissioners of Accounts with the Letter and Findings of His Honor, Thos. F. Gilroy, Mayor, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Incomplete transcript of testimony in unidentified case: pp. 81-126, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Sworn statement of Alexander E. Macdonald re: mental and physical condition of Patrick Trenor, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Notice of Execution of Commission. In the Matter of the Application for the Appointment of a Committee of the Person and Property of Joseph G. Creamer, an alleged insane person, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Expert testimony of A.E. Macdonald in unidentified case, Subsubseries 11
      - "MSS" (direct examination by Mr. Peckham and cross examination by Mr. Brown, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "Manuscript" (cross examination -- continued), 1876 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "Manuscript No. 2" (cross examination resumed by Mr. Brown and redirected by Mr. Peckham), 1876 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Memberships and Medical Conferences, Subseries B
    - 12th International Medical Congress, Moscow: various materials, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - British Medical Association Session, Edinburgh: various materials, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 14th International Medical Congress, Madrid: Related correspondence, newspapers, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 14th International Medical Congress, Madrid: Mementos, receipts, writings, printed pamphlets, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 15th International Medical Congress, Lisbon: Related correspondence, newspaper articles, printed pamphlets, etc., 1906 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous membership materials, various (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Membership certificates, various (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Medical Society of the City and County of New York, 1878
      - New York Medico Legal Society, 1882
      - The New York Academy of Medicine, 1885
      - Boston Gynaecological Society, 1885
      - Medico-Psychological Association, 1898
      - Medical Association of the Greater City of New York, 1902
    - A.E. Macdonald's New York State physician's license (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Other, Subseries C
    - University of the City of New York. Medical Department. Spring Session, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - University of the City of New York. Medical Deparment. Spring Session, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - University of the City of New York. Medical Department. Spring Session, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - University of the City of New York. Medical Department. Spring Session, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous other course and lecture bulletins (photocopies), 1875-87 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Vial of morphine sulphate, undated (Box 8, Bag 1)
    - Vial of ergot aseptic, undated (Box 4, Bag 1)
- Biographical and Personal Material, Series IV
  Biographical and Personal Material contains material relating to Dr. Macdonald's personal life, including correspondence with family and friends; financial information; marriage and citizenship papers; diplomas; membership information for social clubs to which Dr. Macdonald belonged and a host of ephemera, including menus, invitations, and business cards.
  - Various certificates including: (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Second class certificate, School of Military Instruction, Canada, 1864
    - First class certificate, School of Military Instruction, Canada, 1865
    - US citizenship certificate, 1871
    - US cititzenship certificate, duplicate, 1871; oversized
    - LLD degree from the University of the City of New York, 1881
    - Certificate of clerkship for admission to practice law in New York State, 1881
    - Marriage certificate, Portland, Maine, 1883
  - Correspondence, various; Including letters to A.E. Macdonald from his children and to Mrs. Macdonald from various individuals following the death of A.E. Macdonald. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Memberships, various; Various materials related to A.E. Macdonald's membership in social clubs including the Lotus Club, the Union of the Titans, the Masons, and the Alumni Association of the Medical Department of the University of the City of New York. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Other, Printed, typescript, and manuscript ephemera, including menus, mementos, business cards, bank statements, personal account records, and poetry. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Manuscripts, Series V
  The Manuscripts series contains (a) Dr. Macdonald's Bound Diaries and Writings, which are, for the most part, daily diaries as well as some student notes and notes on various medical subjects, case records, and patient property logs; (b) his Writings, which include both handwritten manuscripts and typescripts ofpapers, speeches, lectures, and presentations on a host of medical topics including rape, identity, malpractice, medical jurisprudence, homicide, and pregnancy, to name a few; and (c) Miscellaneous Notes which include a sizable number of lists, calculations and other scraps (many of which are not legible).
  - Bound diaries and notebooks, Subseries A
    - A.E. Macdonald Notebooks (leather bound), Subsubseries 1
      - Vol. I [Daily diary], June 1-Dec. 9, 1873 (Box 5, Wrapper 1)
      - Vol. II [The Life of A.E. Macdonald; Daily diary], Dec. 10-June 19. 1874 (Box 5, Wrapper 2)
      - Vol. III [Daily diary], June 20-Dec. 31, 1874 (Box 5, Wrapper 3)
      - Vol. IV [Recollections of a Busy Life; Daily diary]; flip side [Chief of Staff's Absence Book], Jan. 1-May 31, 1875 (Box 5, Wrapper 4)
      - Vol. V [Lives of the Saints; Daily diary], June 1-Dec. 15, 1875 (Box 5, Wrapper 5)
      - Vol. VI [Daily diary], Dec. 16-June 24, 1876 (Box 5, Wrapper 6)
      - Vol. VII [Daily diary], June 25-Dec. 31, 1876 (Box 5, Wrapper 7)
      - Vol. VIII [Daily diary], Jan. 1-Apr. 22, 1877 (Box 5, Wrapper 8)
      - Vol. IX [Daily diary], Apr. 23-Aug. 12, 1877 (Box 5, Wrapper 9)
      - Vol. X [Daily diary], Aug. 13-Nov. 20, 1877 (Box 5, Wrapper 10)
      - Vol. XI [Daily diary], Dec. 1-June 8, 1878 (Box 5, Wrapper 11)
      - Vol. XII [Daily diary], June 9-Dec. 19, 1878 (Box 5, Wrapper 12)
      - Vol. XIII [Daily diary], Dec. 20-June 30, 1878 (Box 5, Wrapper 13)
      - Vol. XIV [Daily diary], July 1, 1879-Jan. 8, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 14)
      - Vol. XV [Daily diary], Jan. 9-July 18, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 15)
      - Vol. XVI [Daily diary], July 19-Jan. 30, 1881 (Box 5, Wrapper 16)
      - Vol. XVII [Daily diary], Feb. 1-Nov. 16, 1881 (Box 5, Wrapper 17)
      - Vol. XVIII [Daily diary], Nov. 17-Sept. 4, 1882 (Box 5, Wrapper 18)
      - Vol. XIX [Daily diary], Sept. 20-May 31, 1883 (Box 5, Wrapper 19)
      - Vol. XX [Daily diary], June 1-Feb. 29, 1884 (Box 5, Wrapper 20)
      - Vol. XXI [Daily diary], March 1-Nov. 20, 1884 (Box 5, Wrapper 21)
      - Vol. XXII [Daily diary], Dec. 1-Aug. 31, 1885 (Box 5, Wrapper 22)
      - [Daily diary], April 7, 1893-Dec. 31, 1895 (Box 5, Wrapper 23)
      - [Daily diary], Jan. 1, 1896-Dec. 31, 1899 (Box 5, Wrapper 24)
      - [Notes on Physiology], July 28, 1868 (Box 5, Wrapper 25)
      - [Notebook No. 2, Practice of Medicine], Nov. 15, 1869 (Box 5, Wrapper 26)
      - [Notebook No. 3, notes on various medical topics including "Muscles of Hand"; "Circulation"; "Fractures"; etc.], Dec. 20, 1869 (Box 5, Wrapper 27)
      - Vol. I [Ward's Island], Oct. 6, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 28)
      - Vol. II [miscellaneous notes], Oct. 19, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 29)
      - Vol. III [miscellaneous notes], Oct. 20, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 30)
      - Vol. IV [miscellaneous notes], Nov. 7, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 31)
      - Vol. V [miscellaneous notes], Nov. 30, 1880 (Box 5, Wrapper 32)
      - Vol. VI [Univ. of New York, Law Department; Part I, Chap. I], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 33)
      - Vol. VIII [Univ. of New York, Law Department; Exam], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 34)
      - Vol. IX [Univ. of New York, Law Department; Part II, Chap. IV], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 35)
      - Vol. X [Chap. V], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 36)
      - [Valuables of patients], 1883-1887 (Box 5, Wrapper 37)
      - [Notes and Queries], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 38)
      - [Notes on Lead Posioning], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 39)
      - [Wm. F. Turner, Patient Notes], undated (Box 5, Wrapper 40)
      - [Diary], Jan. 1, 1900-July 10, 1906 (Box 5, Wrapper 41)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 5, Wrapper 42)
    - Paper Cover Flip Notepads, Subsubseries 2
      - [Daily Notes], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [St. Louis], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Commission [?]], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Commission [?] Visit], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Untitled], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Untitled], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Daily Notes], 1903 (Box 6, Wrapper 2)
      - [Untitled], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 2)
      - [Untitled], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 2)
    - Half Leather/Marbled Paper Bound Ledgers, Subsubseries 3
      - [Patients' property], 1876-1883 (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Notes on mania], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 2)
      - [Notes on dementia], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
      - [Notes on abortion], undated (Box 6, Wrapper 1)
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks, Subsubseries 4
      - [Miniature leather notebook], undated (Box 7, Envelope 1)
      - [Address Book], undated (Box 7, Envelope 2)
      - [Cloth diary: Exercises; letters sent/received], 1863 (Box 7, Envelope 3)
      - [Cash Book], 1869-1870 (Box 7, Envelope 4)
      - [Patients' property], 1883-1887 (Box 7, Envelope 5)
      - [Daily diary; expenses; class time table; rifle shooting scores; letters received and posted], 1863-64 (Box 7, Wrapper 1)
      - [A.E. Macdonald, Fourth Class, Model Grammar School], undated (Box 7, Wrapper 2)
  - Writings, Subseries B
    - "Medical Jurisprudence, Lecture First - Univ. Med. Coll,", 1875 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - G. A. Blumer, The Medical and Material Aspects of Industrial Employment for the Insane, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Announcements," with printed program "Manhattan State Hospital, East (Ward's Island), Programme of Sports by Patients and Employees, Independence Day, July 4, 1904, on the Grounds of the Hospital," (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - A.E. Macdonald, "Tent treatment for the tuberculous insane,", undated; 3 copies (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - A.E. Macdonald, "Tent life for the tuberculous and other classes of insane,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Notes on camp treatment for tuberculosis insane,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Training school for nurses,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Acknowledgments,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Medical Staff,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Overcrowding,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Amusements,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "The punishment of the insane for criminal acts,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - J.W. Putnam, "Paranoia as seen in criminals,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Discussion, Dr. Punton's paper, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "X rays in anthropometrical signalment,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "For Better For Worse in Egypt,", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Rape," pp. 1-51, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Identity," pp. 1-27, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Malpractice," pp. 1-16, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Homicide" (incomplete), pp. 1-8, 10-50, A, C-I, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Signs of Pregnancy," pp. 1-23, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Ward,", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Signs of Delivery," pp. 1-6, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Duration of Pregnancy," pp. 1-16, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "Responsibility" (incomplete), pp. 1-15, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-46, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-6, with two pages of correspondence (incomplete), undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Untitled, p. 1-13, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-41, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-63, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Untitled (incomplete), pp. 1-55, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-30, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Untitled, pp. 1-47, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Untitled (incomplete), pp. 2-25, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Untitled (incomplete), pp. 1-6, 9-27, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Subseries C
    - Handwritten notes, lists, calculations, receipts, ticket stubs, ink drawing, various (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Two envelopes of handwritten notes, lists, ticket stubs, and related items, various (Box 6, Envelope 1)
    - Handwritten notes, lists, calculations, receipts, various (Box 6, Envelope 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, Series VI
  Newspaper Clippings contains clippings from 1865 to 1906 on a host of issues ranging from the treatment of the insane; management of the New York institutions and investigations thereof; prominent legal cases relating to Dr. Macdonald, the asylums and/or patients; lunacy laws; as well as reports and reviews of Dr. Macdonald's speaking engagements at various dinners, receptions, and banquets.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 1, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 2, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 1, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 2, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 1, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 2, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 1, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 2, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 3, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 1, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Newspaper Clippings, pt. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Photographs, Series VII
  - 16 card-mounted photographs (platinum prints?) and reproductions of the Tuberculosis tent city at the Manhattan State Hospital, East, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Original photographs (various processes) of subjects including Dr. Macdonald's son, Charles; the Medical Superintendents of American Insane Institutions, 1878; and other unidentified places as well as multiple reproductions of an image of Dr. Macdonald (Box 8, Folder 2)
Provenance
Archive purchased by NYAM from Peter Keyes/Oxbow Books in 2005, with additional gifts of related items from same.